<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Brian Gibbs | Shariq Mohammed</title>
    <link>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/authors/brian-gibbs/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/authors/brian-gibbs/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Brian Gibbs</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 07 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>Brian Gibbs</title>
      <link>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/authors/brian-gibbs/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Association Between Tourniquet Use and Patient‑Reported Outcomes Following Total Knee Arthroplasty: A Multicenter Comparison</title>
      <link>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/gibbs2025association/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/gibbs2025association/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Journal of Bone &amp;amp; Joint Surgery&lt;/em&gt; (2025).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Background: Total knee arthroplasty (TKA) is among the most commonly performed elective procedures. Tourniquet use remains debated regarding patient outcomes and postoperative experience. Methods: Within the PEPPER trial framework, 5,684 primary TKAs were analyzed; 4,866 (85.6%) used a tourniquet and 818 (14.4%) did not. Primary outcomes were KOOS‑JR, PROMIS‑PH10, and numeric pain rating, collected preoperatively and at 1, 3, and 6 months. Secondary outcomes included length of stay, discharge disposition, analgesic consumption, and complications. Multivariable analyses assessed associations between tourniquet use and PROMs. Results: The percentage achieving MCID for KOOS‑JR differed at 1 month (tourniquet 55.4% vs no‑tourniquet 47.9%) but not at 3 or 6 months. No differences were observed for PROMIS‑PH10 or pain at any time point, nor for opioid use, operative time, LOS, wound complications, or readmissions. Conclusions: Tourniquet use conferred a small early KOOS‑JR advantage at 1 month that was not sustained; overall, tourniquet use did not have a clinically meaningful impact on PROMs.  &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
