<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Shariq Mohammed</title>
    <link>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Shariq Mohammed</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 20 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>Shariq Mohammed</title>
      <link>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Imaging and complex-structured data applications</title>
      <link>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/research/applications/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/research/applications/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We develop statistical models to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;identify associations between complex-structured data (imaging, spatial-genomic, geospatial, digital) from multi-platform data sources,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;predict clinical characteristics of interest by integrating biomarkers generated from complex-structured data, and&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;understand the biological relevance and implications of our findings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our methods are developed in the context of various diseases such as cancer and neurodegenerative (Alzheimer&amp;rsquo;s) diseases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Statistical methods for the analysis of complex-structured biomedical data</title>
      <link>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/research/methods/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/research/methods/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We develop innovative statistical methodology that leverages structural and biological information in the data. To address the challenges of handling complex-structured data, we develop and employ methods at the interface of hierarchical Bayesian modeling, variable selection, geometric/functional data analysis and spatial statistics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Integrative Bayesian models using post-selective inference: a case study in radiogenomics</title>
      <link>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/panigrahi2020integrative/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/panigrahi2020integrative/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Biometrics (Just Accepted)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Identifying direct links between gene pathways and clinical endpoints for highly fatal diseases such as cancer is a formidable task. Integrative analyses play a crucial role in modeling these links by relying upon associations between a wealth of intermediary variables and genomic measurements. Motivated to harness phenotypic information about tumors towards a molecular characterization of low-grade gliomas, we develop a data driven Bayesian framework to define sharp models, and calibrate accurately and efficiently uncertainties associated with the promising biological findings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Bayesian methods we propose in the article (i) are amenable to a flexible class of adaptive models, determined via a complex interplay between signals sifted from variable selection algorithms and domain specific knowledge; (ii) have the advantage of computationally efficient high dimensional inference due to a focus on sharp models with fewer parameters, when compared to their non-adaptive counterparts; (iii) exhibit a significantly better reconciliation between model adaptivity and inferential power than state-of-art approaches, when constrained by the curse of dimensionality. Our main workforce involves a carefully constructed conditional likelihood and utilizes a reparameterization map to obtain compact formulae for a selection-corrected posterior. Deploying our methods to investigate radiogenomic characteristics for diffuse low-grade gliomas, we successfully uncover associations between several biologically important gene pathways and patient survival times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Comparative study of radiologists vs machine learning in differentiating biopsy-proven pseudoprogression and true progression in diffuse gliomas</title>
      <link>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/turk2022comparative/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/turk2022comparative/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Neuroscience Informatics&lt;/em&gt; (2022).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Background and Purpose&lt;/strong&gt; MRI features of tumor progression and
pseudoprogression may be indistinguishable especially without enhancing
portion of the diffuse gliomas. Our aim is to discriminate these two
conditions using radiomics and machine learning algorithm and to compare
them with human observations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Materials and Methods&lt;/strong&gt; Three consecutive MRI studies before a
definitive biopsy in 43 diffuse glioma patients (7 pseudoprogression and
36 true progression cases) who underwent treatment were evaluated. Two
neuroradiologists reviewed pre- and post-contrast T1, T2, FLAIR, ADC,
rCBV, rCBF, K2, and MTT maps. Patterns of enhancement, ADC maps, rCBV,
rCBF, MTT, K2 values, and perilesional FLAIR signal intensity changes
were recorded. Odds ratios (OR) for each descriptor, raters&#39; success in
predicting true and pseudoprogression, and inter-observer reliability
were calculated using the R statistics software. Unpaired Student&amp;rsquo;s
t-test and receiver operating characteristic (ROC) analysis were applied
to compare the texture parameters and histogram analysis of pseudo- and
true progression groups. All first-order and second-order image texture
features and shape features were used to train and test the Random
Forest classifier (RFC). Observers&#39; success and RFC were compared.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Results&lt;/strong&gt; Observers could not identify true progression in the first
visit. However, accuracy of the RFC model was 81%. For the second and
third visits, the rater&amp;rsquo;s success of prediction was between 62% and 72%.
The accuracy for the second and last visit with RFC was 75% and 81%.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusions&lt;/strong&gt; Random Forest classifier was more successful than human
observations in predicting pseudoprogression using MRI.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cellular engagement and interaction in the tumor microenvironment predict non-response to PD-1/PD-L1 inhibitors in metastatic non-small cell lung cancer</title>
      <link>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/qin2022cellular/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/qin2022cellular/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Scientific Reports&lt;/em&gt; (2021).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Immune checkpoint inhibitors (ICI) with anti-PD-1/PD-L1 agents have improved the survival of patients with metastatic non-small cell lung cancer (mNSCLC). Tumor PD-L1 expression is an imperfect biomarker as it does not capture the complex interactions between constituents of the tumor microenvironment (TME). Using multiplex fluorescent immunohistochemistry (mfIHC), we modeled the TME to study the influence of cellular distribution and engagement on response to ICI in mNSCLC. We performed mfIHC on pretreatment tissue from patients with mNSCLC who received ICI. We used primary antibodies against CD3, CD8, CD163, PD-L1, pancytokeratin, and FOXP3; simple and complex phenotyping as well as spatial analyses was performed. We analyzed 68 distinct samples from 52 patients with mNSCLC. Patients were 39&amp;ndash;79 years old (median 67); 44% were male and 75% had adenocarcinoma histology. The most used ICI was atezolizumab (48%). The percentage of PD-L1 positive epithelial tumor cells (EC), degree of cytotoxic T lymphocyte (CTL) engagement with EC, and degree of CTL engagement with helper T lymphocytes (HTL) were significantly lower in non-responders versus responders (p = 0.0163, p = 0.0026 and p = 0.0006, respectively). The combination of these 3 characteristics generated the best sensitivity and specificity to predict non-response to ICI and was also associated with shortened overall survival (p = 0.0271). The combination of low CTL engagement with EC and HTL along with low expression of EC PD-L1 represents a state of impaired endogenous immune reactivity. Together, they more precisely identified non-responders to ICI compared to PD-L1 alone and illustrate the importance of cellular interactions in the TME.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Network-based Modeling of COVID-19 Dynamics: Early Pandemic Spread in India</title>
      <link>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/bhattacharyya2021network/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/bhattacharyya2021network/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Journal of the Indian Statistical Association &lt;em&gt;(Just Accepted)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Modeling the dynamics of COVID-19 pandemic spread is a challenging and relevant problem.  Established models for the epidemic spread such as compartmental epidemiological models e.g. Susceptible-Infected-Recovered (SIR) models and its variants, have been discussed extensively in the literature and utilized to forecast the growth of the pandemic across different hot-spots in the world. The standard formulations of SIR models rely upon summary-level data, which may not be  able to fully capture the complete dynamics of the pandemic growth. Since the disease spreads from carriers to susceptible individuals via some form of contact, it inherently relies upon a network of individuals for its growth, with edges established via direct interaction, such as shared physical proximity. Using spatial and individual-level COVID-19 data from the early days (January 30 to April 15, 2020) of the pandemic in India, and under a network-based SIR model framework, we performed state-specific forecasting under multiple scenarios characterized by the basic reproduction number of COVID-19 across 34 Indian states and union territories. We validated our short-term projections using observed case counts and the long-term projections using national sero-survey findings. Based on healthcare availability data, we also performed projections to assess the burdens on the infrastructure along the spectrum of the pandemic growth. We have developed an &lt;a href=&#34;https://bayesrx.shinyapps.io/COV-N/&#34;&gt;interactive dashboard&lt;/a&gt; summarizing our results. Our predictions successfully identified the initial hot-spots of India such as Maharashtra and Delhi, and those that emerged later, such as Madhya Pradesh and Kerala. These models have the potential to inform appropriate policies for isolation and mitigation strategies to contain the pandemic, through a phased approach  by appropriate resource prioritization and allocation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>GaWRDenMap: A quantitative framework to study the local variation in cell-cell interactions in pancreatic disease subtypes</title>
      <link>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/krishnan2022gawrdenmap/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/krishnan2022gawrdenmap/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Scientific Reports&lt;/em&gt; (2022)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Spatial pattern modelling concepts are being increasingly used in capturing disease heterogeneity. Quantification of heterogeneity in the tumor microenvironment is extremely important in pancreatic ductal adenocarcinoma (PDAC), which has been shown to co-occur with other pancreatic diseases and neoplasms with certain attributes that make visual discrimination difficult. In this paper, we propose the GaWRDenMap framework, that utilizes the concepts of geographically weighted regression (GWR) and a density function-based classification model, and apply it to a cohort of multiplex immunofluorescence images from patients belonging to six different pancreatic diseases. We used an internal cohort of 228 patients comprised of 34 Chronic Pancreatitis (CP), 71 PDAC, 70 intraductal papillary mucinous neoplasm (IPMN), 16 mucinous cystic neoplasm (MCN), 29 pancreatic intraductal neoplasia (PanIN) and 8  IPMN-associated PDAC patients. We utilize GWR to model the relationship between epithelial cells and immune cells on a spatial grid. The GWR model estimates were used to generate density signatures which were used in subsequent pairwise classification models to distinguish between any two pairs of disease groups. Image-level, as well as subject-level analysis, were performed. When applied to this dataset, our classification model showed significant discrimination ability in multiple pairwise comparisons, in comparison to commonly used abundance-based metrics, like the Morisita-Horn index. The model was able to  best discriminate between CP and PDAC at both the subject- and image-levels. It was also able to reasonably discriminate between PDAC and IPMN. These results point to a potential difference in the spatial arrangement of epithelial and immune cells between CP, PDAC and IPMN, that could be of high  diagnostic significance. Further validation on a more comprehensive dataset would be warranted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>BS 730 - Introduction to R: Software for Statistical Computing</title>
      <link>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/teaching/bs730/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/teaching/bs730/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quantifying T2-FLAIR mismatch using geographically weighted regression and predicting molecular status in lower-grade gliomas</title>
      <link>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/mohammed2021quantifying/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/mohammed2021quantifying/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;American Journal of Neuroradiology&lt;/em&gt; (2021).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Nominated for 2021 Lucien Levy Best Research Article.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ajnrblog.org/2022/03/28/journal-announces-this-years-lucien-levy-best-research-article-award-winner-and-nominees/&#34;&gt;AJNR Blog Annoucement&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Background and Purpose&lt;/em&gt;. T2-FLAIR mismatch sign is a validated imaging sign of IDH-mutant 1p/19q non-codeleted gliomas. It is identified by radiologists through visual inspection of pre-operative MRI scans, and has been shown to identify IDH-mutant 1p/19q non-codeleted gliomas with high positive predictive value. We have developed an approach to quantify the T2-FLAIR mismatch signature, and use it to predict molecular status of lower-grade gliomas (LGG).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Materials and Methods&lt;/em&gt;. We used multi-parametric MRI scans and segmentation labels of 108 pre-operative LGG tumors from The Cancer Imaging Archive. Clinical information and T2-FLAIR mismatch sign labels were obtained from supplementary material of relevant publications. We adopted an objective analytical approach to estimate this sign through a geographically weighted regression (GWR), and use the residuals for each case to construct a probability density function (serving as residual signature). These functions are then analyzed using an appropriate statistical framework.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Results&lt;/em&gt;. We observe statistically significant (p-value = 0.05) differences between the averages of residual signatures for IDH-mutated 1p/19q non-codeleted class of tumors versus other categories. Our classifier predicts these cases with area under the curve (AUC) of 0.98, high specificity and sensitivity. It also predicts T2-FLAIR mismatch sign within these cases with an AUC of 0.93.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Conclusions&lt;/em&gt;. Based on this retrospective study, we show that GWR-based residual signatures are highly informative of T2-FLAIR mismatch sign, and can identify IDH mutation and 1p/19q codeletion status with high predictive power. The utility of proposed quantification of T2-FLAIR mismatch sign can be potentially validated through a prospective multi-institutional study.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tumor radiogenomics with Bayesian layered variable selection</title>
      <link>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/mohammed2021tumor/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/mohammed2021tumor/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We propose a statistical framework to integrate radiological magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) and genomic data to identify the underlying radiogenomic associations in lower grade gliomas (LGG). We devise a novel imaging phenotype by dividing the tumor region into concentric spherical layers that mimics the tumor evolution process. MRI data within each layer is represented by voxel&amp;ndash;intensity-based probability density functions which capture the complete information about tumor heterogeneity. Under a Riemannian-geometric framework these densities are mapped to a vector of principal component scores which act as imaging phenotypes. Subsequently, we build Bayesian variable selection models for each layer with the imaging phenotypes as the response and the genomic markers as predictors. Our novel hierarchical prior formulation incorporates the interior-to-exterior structure of the layers, and the correlation between the genomic markers. We employ a computationally-efficient Expectation&amp;ndash;Maximization-based strategy for estimation. Simulation studies demonstrate the superior performance of our approach compared to other approaches. With a focus on the cancer driver genes in LGG, we discuss some biologically relevant findings. Genes implicated with survival and oncogenesis are identified as being associated with the spherical layers, which could potentially serve as early-stage diagnostic markers for disease monitoring, prior to routine invasive approaches.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Spatial Tweedie exponential dispersion models: An application to insurance rate-making</title>
      <link>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/halder2020spatial/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/halder2020spatial/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Scandinavian Actuarial Journal&lt;/em&gt; (2021).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this paper we propose a statistical modeling framework that contributes to advancing methods for modeling insurance policy premium in the actuarial literature. Specification of separate frequency and severity models, accounting for territorial risk and performing accurate inference are some of the challenges actuaries face while modeling policy premium. We focus on building a methodology that builds parsimonious and interpretable models for modeling policy premium. Policy premiums are characterized to follow a semi-continuous probability distribution, featuring a non-zero probability mass at zero along with a positive continuous support. Interpretability is a concern when quantifying risks that policy premium face from spatial variation. Risk conferred from spatial sources is often treated as an unobserved. Commonly used strategies in the literature are known to successfully quantify the variation, but do not necessarily produce interpretable estimates. Furthermore, resorting to two-part frequency-severity models leaves the actuary indecisive about the specification of covariates and spatial effects. The proposed methods in the paper considers a more parsimonious approach by resorting to zero-adjusted models for policy premium, that models both the mean policy-premium and the associated dispersion around the mean. Quantification of variation from spatial sources is proposed for the mean model. Allowing for a non-constant dispersion across observations results in a better estimate of the underlying variability, producing superior estimates for coefficients. The novelty of the proposed approach lies in the framework developed, that allows for joint estimation of effect of policy or individual characteristics on both the mean policy premium and dispersion, while quantifying spatial variability in the mean model. The developed methods are applied to a database featuring policy premiums arising from the collision coverage in insurance policies for motor vehicles within the state of Connecticut, USA for the year 2008.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>RADIOHEAD: Radiogenomic analysis incorporating tumor heterogeneity in imagine through densities</title>
      <link>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/mohammed2021radiohead/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/mohammed2021radiohead/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Annals of Applied Statistics&lt;/em&gt; (2021).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recent technological advancements have enabled detailed investigation of associations between the molecular architecture and tumor heterogeneity, through multi-source integration of radiological imaging and genomic (radiogenomic) data. In this paper, we integrate and harness radiogenomic data in patients with lower grade gliomas (LGG), a type of brain cancer, in order to develop a regression framework called RADIOHEAD (RADIOgenomic analysis incorporating tumor HEterogeneity in imAging through Densities) to identify radiogenomic associations. Imaging data is represented through voxel intensity probability density functions of tumor sub-regions obtained from multimodal magnetic resonance imaging, and genomic data through molecular signatures in the form of pathway enrichment scores corresponding to their gene expression profiles. Employing a Riemannian-geometric framework for principal component analysis on the set of probability densities functions, we map each probability density to a vector of principal component scores, which are then included as predictors in a Bayesian regression model with the pathway enrichment scores as the response. Variable selection compatible with the grouping structure amongst the predictors induced through the tumor sub-regions is carried out under a group spike-and-slab prior. A Bayesian false discovery rate mechanism is then used to infer significant associations based on the posterior distribution of the regression coefficients. Our analyses reveal several pathways relevant to LGG etiology (such as synaptic transmission, nerve impulse and neurotransmitter pathways), to have significant associations with the corresponding imaging-based predictors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Scalable spatio-temporal Bayesian analysis of high-dimensional electroencephalography data</title>
      <link>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/mohammed2021scalable/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/mohammed2021scalable/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Canadian Journal of Statistics&lt;/em&gt; (2021).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We present a scalable Bayesian modeling approach for identifying brain regions that respond to a certain stimulus and use them to classify subjects. We specifically deal with multi-subject electroencephalography (EEG) data with a binary response distinguishing between alcoholic and control groups. The covariates are matrix-variate with measurements taken for each subject at different locations across multiple time points. EEG data has a complex structure with both spatial and temporal attributes to it. We use a divide-and-conquer strategy to build multiple local models, that is, one model at each time point separately. We employ Bayesian variable selection approaches using a structured continuous spike-and-slab prior to identify the locations which respond to a certain stimulus. We incorporate the spatio-temporal structure through a Kronecker product of the spatial and temporal correlation matrices. We develop a highly scalable estimation algorithm using likelihood approximation to deal with large number of parameters in the model. Variable selection is done via clustering of the locations based on their duration of activation. We use scoring rules to evaluate the prediction performance. We perform simulation studies to demonstrate the efficiency of our scalable algorithm in terms of estimation and fast computation. We present results using our scalable approach for a case study on multi-subject EEG data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Discriminating pseudoprogression and true progression in diffuse infiltrating glioma using multi-parametric MRI data through deep learning</title>
      <link>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/lee2020discriminating/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/lee2020discriminating/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Scientific Reports&lt;/em&gt; (2020).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Differentiating pseudoprogression from true tumor progression has become a significant challenge in follow-up of diffuse infiltrating gliomas, particularly high grade, which leads to a potential treatment delay for patients with early glioma recurrence. In this study, we proposed to use a multiparametric MRI data as a sequence input for the convolutional neural network with the recurrent neural network based deep learning structure to discriminate between pseudoprogression and true tumor progression. In this study, 43 biopsy-proven patient data identified as diffuse infiltrating glioma patients whose disease progressed/recurred were used. The dataset consists of five original MRI sequences; pre-contrast T1-weighted, post-contrast T1-weighted, T2-weighted, FLAIR, and ADC images as well as two engineered sequences; T1post – T1pre and T2 – FLAIR. Next, we used three CNN-LSTM models with a different set of sequences as input sequences to pass through CNN-LSTM layers. We performed 3-fold cross-validation in the training dataset and generated the boxplot, accuracy, and ROC curve, AUC from each trained model with the test dataset to evaluate models. The mean accuracy for VGG16 models ranged from 0.44 to 0.60 and the mean AUC ranged from 0.47 to 0.59. For CNN-LSTM model, the mean accuracy ranged from 0.62 to 0.75 and the mean AUC ranged from 0.64 to 0.81. The performance of the proposed CNN-LSTM with multiparametric sequence data was found to outperform the popular convolutional CNN with a single MRI sequence. In conclusion, incorporating all available MRI sequences into a sequence input for a CNN-LSTM model improved diagnostic performance for discriminating between pseudoprogression and true tumor progression.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Bayesian 2D functional linear model for gray-level co-occurrence matrices in texture analysis of lower grade gliomas</title>
      <link>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/chekouo2020bayesian/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/chekouo2020bayesian/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;NeuroImage: Clinical&lt;/em&gt; (2020).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In cancer radiomics, textural features evaluated from image intensity-derived gray-level co-occurrence matrices (GLCMs) have been studied to evaluate gray-level spatial dependence within the regions of interest in the brain. Most of these analysis work with summary statistics (or texture-based features) constructed using the GLCM entries, and potentially overlook other structural properties in the GLCM.  In our proposed Bayesian framework, we treat each GLCM  as a realization of a two-dimensional stochastic functional process observed with error at discrete time points. The latent process is then combined with the outcome model to evaluate the prediction performance. We use simulation studies to assess the performance of our method and apply it to data collected from individuals with lower grade gliomas. We found our approach to outperform competing methods that use only summary statistics to predict isocitrate dehydrogenase (IDH) mutation status.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Density-based classification in diabetic retinopathy through thickness of retinal layers from optical coherence tomography</title>
      <link>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/mohammed2020density/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/mohammed2020density/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Scientific Reports&lt;/em&gt; (2020).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Diabetic retinopathy (DR) is a severe retinal disorder that can lead to vision loss, however, its underlying mechanism has not been fully understood. Previous studies have taken advantage of Optical Coherence Tomography (OCT) and shown that the thickness of individual retinal layers are affected in patients with DR. However, most studies analyzed the thickness by calculating summary statistics from retinal thickness maps of the macula region. This study aims to apply a density function-based statistical framework to the thickness data obtained through OCT, and to compare the predictive power of various retinal layers to assess the severity of DR. We used a prototype data set of 107 subjects which are comprised of 38 non-proliferative DR (NPDR), 28 without DR (NoDR), and 41 controls. Based on the thickness profiles, we constructed novel features which capture the variation in the distribution of the pixel-wise retinal layer thicknesses from OCT. We quantified the predictive power of each of the retinal layers to distinguish between all three pairwise comparisons of the severity in DR (NoDR vs NPDR, controls vs NPDR and controls vs NoDR). When applied to this preliminary DR data set, our density-based method demonstrated better predictive results compared with simple summary statistics. Furthermore, our results indicate considerable differences in retinal layer structuring based on the severity of DR. We found that: (a) the outer plexiform layer is the most discriminative layer for classifying NoDR vs NPDR; (b) the outer plexiform, inner nuclear and ganglion cell layers are the strongest biomarkers for discriminating controls from NPDR; and (c) the inner nuclear layer distinguishes best between controls and NoDR.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Classification of high-dimensional electroencephalography data with location selection using structured spike-and-slab prior</title>
      <link>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/mohammed2020classification/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/mohammed2020classification/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Invited for Statistical Analysis and Data Mining Best Paper Session at Joint Statistical Meetings 2022.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://ww2.amstat.org/meetings/jsm/2022/onlineprogram/ActivityDetails.cfm?SessionID=221965&#34;&gt;JSM 2022 Program&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Statistical Analysis and Data Mining: The ASA Data Science Journal&lt;/em&gt; (2020).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the advent of modern technologies, it is increasingly common to deal with data of large dimensions in various scientific fields of study. In this paper, we develop a Bayesian approach for the classification of multi-subject high-dimensional electroencephalography (EEG) data. In this EEG data, we have a matrix of covariates corresponding to each subject from either the alcoholic or control group. The matrix covariates have a natural spatial correlation based on the locations of the brain, and temporal correlation as the measurements are taken over time. We employ a divide and conquer strategy by building multiple local Bayesian models at each time point separately. We incorporate the spatial structure through the structured spike-and-slab prior, which has inherent variable selection properties. The temporal structure is incorporated within the prior by learning from the local model from the previ- ous time point. We pool the information from the local models and use a weighted average to design a prediction method. We perform simulation studies to show the efficiency of our approach and demonstrate the local Bayesian modeling with a case study on EEG data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Predictions, role of interventions and effects of a historic national lockdown in India’s response to the COVID-19 pandemic: data science call to arms</title>
      <link>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/ray2020predictions/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/ray2020predictions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Harvard Data Science Review&lt;/em&gt; (2020).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With only 536 cases and 11 fatalities, India took the historic decision of a 21-day national lockdown on March 25. The lockdown was first extended to May 3 soon after the analysis of this paper was completed, and then to May 18 while this paper was being revised. In this paper, we use a Bayesian extension of the Susceptible-Infected-Removed (eSIR) model designed for intervention forecasting to study the short- and long-term impact of an initial 21-day lockdown on the total number of COVID-19 infections in India compared to other less severe non-pharmaceutical interventions. We compare effects of hypothetical durations of lockdown on reducing the number of active and new infections. We find that the lockdown, if implemented correctly, can reduce the total number of cases in the short term, and buy India invaluable time to prepare its healthcare and disease-monitoring system. Our analysis shows we need to have some measures of suppression in place after the lockdown for increased benefit (as measured by reduction in the number of cases). A longer lockdown between 42-56 days is preferable to substantially “flatten the curve” when compared to 21-28 days of lockdown. Our models focus solely on projecting the number of COVID-19 infections and thus, inform policymakers about one aspect of this multi-faceted decision-making problem. We conclude with a discussion on the pivotal role of increased testing, reliable and transparent data, proper uncertainty quantification, accurate interpretation of forecasting models, reproducible data science methods and tools that can enable data-driven policymaking during a pandemic. Our software products are available at &lt;a href=&#34;covind19.org&#34;&gt;covind19.org&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Regional contact networks and the pandemic spread of COVID-19 in India</title>
      <link>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/posts/bhattacharyya2020regional/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/posts/bhattacharyya2020regional/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Predictions to enable State-level Surge Preparedness in moving from Containment to Mitigation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The medium.com article can be &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@veerab_12080/regional-contact-networks-and-the-pandemic-spread-of-covid-19-in-india-28b3b3aa2161&#34;&gt;found here&lt;/a&gt;. To explore the results under different scenarios for the spread of infection, we have developed an R Shiny app which can be accessed &lt;a href=&#34;https://bayesrx.shinyapps.io/COV-N/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Covid-19: India must urgently manage regional contact networks</title>
      <link>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/posts/baladandayuthapani2020covid/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/posts/baladandayuthapani2020covid/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;An Op-Ed on bloombergquint.com can be &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bloombergquint.com/coronavirus-outbreak/covid-19-india-must-urgently-manage-regional-contact-networks&#34;&gt;found here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Biomedical applications of geometric functional data analysis</title>
      <link>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/matuk2020biomedical/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/matuk2020biomedical/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Handbook of Variational Methods for Nonlinear Geometric Data&lt;/em&gt; - Springer (2020).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this chapter, we describe several biomedical applications of geometric functional data analysis methods for modeling probability density functions, amplitude and phase components in functional data, and shapes of curves and surfaces. We begin by reviewing parameterization-invariant Riemannian metrics and corresponding simplifying square-root transforms for each case. These tools allow for computationally efficient implementations of statistical procedures on the appropriate representation spaces, including computation of the Karcher mean and exploration of variability via principal component analysis. We then showcase applications of these tools in multiple biomedical case studies based on various datasets including Glioblastoma Multiforme tumors, Diffusion Tensor Magnetic Resonance Image-based white matter tracts and fractional anisotropy functions, electrocardiogram signals, endometrial tissue surfaces and subcortical surfaces in the brain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Historic 21-day lockdown, predictions for lockdown effects and the role of data in this crisis of virus in India</title>
      <link>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/posts/salvatore2020historic/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/posts/salvatore2020historic/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The medium.com article can be &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@covind_19/historic-lockdown-prediction-models-to-study-lockdown-effects-and-the-role-of-data-in-the-crisis-a0afeeec5a6&#34;&gt;found here&lt;/a&gt;. Daily updates of the plots can be found on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://umich-biostatistics.shinyapps.io/covid19/&#34;&gt;R shiny app here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Predictions and role of interventions for COVID-19 outbreak in India</title>
      <link>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/posts/ray2020predictions/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/posts/ray2020predictions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The medium.com article can be &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@covind_19/predictions-and-role-of-interventions-for-covid-19-outbreak-in-india-52903e2544e6&#34;&gt;found here&lt;/a&gt;. The full report can be &lt;a href=&#34;https://sph.umich.edu/precision-health-data-science/research/pdf/COVReport_Final_20200320.pdf&#34;&gt;downloaded here&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Spatial risk estimation in Tweedie compound Poisson double generalized linear models</title>
      <link>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/halder2019spatial/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/halder2019spatial/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tweedie exponential dispersion family constitutes a fairly rich sub-class of the celebrated exponential family. In particular, a member, compound Poisson gamma (CP-g) model has seen extensive use over the past decade for modeling mixed response featuring exact zeros with a continuous response from a gamma distribution. This paper proposes a framework to perform residual analysis on CP-g double generalized linear models for spatial uncertainty quantification. Approximations are introduced to proposed framework making the procedure scalable, without compromise in accuracy of estimation and model complexity; accompanied by sensitivity analysis to model mis-specification. Proposed framework is applied to modeling spatial uncertainty in insurance loss costs arising from automobile collision coverage. Scalability is demonstrated by choosing sizable spatial reference domains comprised of groups of states within the United States of America.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Computational Biotatistics and Survival Analysis</title>
      <link>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/teaching/cbsa2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/teaching/cbsa2019/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is a workshop taught at &lt;a href=&#34;https://actrec.gov.in/&#34;&gt;Tata Memorial Centre Advanced Centre for Treatment, Research and Education in Cancer&lt;/a&gt;, Navi Mumbai, India during December 2019.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;instructor-bhramar-mukherjee&#34;&gt;Instructor: Bhramar Mukherjee&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Battle of Two Cultures &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/files/cbsa2019/Lecture-0.pptx&#34;&gt;Download&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Model Selection &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/files/cbsa2019/Lecture-1.ppt&#34;&gt;Download&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shrinkage Methods for Variable Selection &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/files/cbsa2019/Lecture-2.ppt&#34;&gt;Download&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Classification and Regression Trees and Random Forests &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/files/cbsa2019/Lecture-3.ppt&#34;&gt;Download&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Electronic Health Records: Michigan Genomics Initiative &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/files/cbsa2019/EHR-Lecture.pptx&#34;&gt;Download&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;references&#34;&gt;References&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/files/cbsa2019/PenalizedCoxRegression.pdf&#34;&gt;Penalized Cox Regression&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/files/cbsa2019/Super-Learner-In-Prediction.pdf&#34;&gt;Super Learner&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;instructor-shariq-mohammed&#34;&gt;Instructor: Shariq Mohammed&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt; implementations and the materials from this workshop are as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/files/cbsa2019/0-general-information.html&#34;&gt;General Information&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/files/cbsa2019/1-intro-to-survival.html&#34;&gt;Introduction to Survival Analysis using R&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/files/cbsa2019/2-power-and-sample-size.html&#34;&gt;Power and Sample Size Calculations in Survival Data&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/files/cbsa2019/3-variable-selection.html&#34;&gt;High-Dimensional Variable Selection Methods&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/files/cbsa2019/3-exercise-variable-selection.html&#34;&gt;Exercise: High-Dimensional Variable Selection Methods&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/files/cbsa2019/4-complex-survival-models.html&#34;&gt;Complex Models for Survival Data&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The data sets used can be downloaded below&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Data used in &lt;em&gt;High-Dimensional Variable Selection Methods&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/files/cbsa2019/variable_selection_data.csv&#34;&gt;Download&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Data for exercise in &lt;em&gt;High-Dimensional Variable Selection Methods&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/files/cbsa2019/exercise_data.csv&#34;&gt;Download&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Data used for &lt;em&gt;Penalized Cox Regression&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/files/cbsa2019/coxnet.RDS&#34;&gt;Download&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bayesian variable selection using spike-and-slab priors with application to high dimensional electroencephalography data by local modelling</title>
      <link>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/mohammed2019bayesian/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/mohammed2019bayesian/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Journal of the Royal Statistical Society: Series C (Applied Statistics)&lt;/em&gt; (2019).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because of the immense technological advances, very often we encounter data in high dimensions. Any set of measurements taken at multiple time points for multiple subjects leads to data of more than two dimensions (a matrix of covariates for each subject). We present a Bayesian variable‐selection method to identify the active regions in the brain as a response to a certain stimulus. We build binary classification models of subject level responses by using binary regression with Gaussian models on the latent variables. We also study the scaled normal priors on the latent variables, as they cover a large family of distributions. We use continuous spike‐and‐slab priors to incorporate variable selection within the modelling. Because of the computational complexity, we build many local (at different time points) models and make predictions by utilizing the temporal structure between the local models. We perform two‐stage variable selection for each of these local models. We demonstrate the effectiveness of such modelling through the results of a simulation study. We then present the performance of these models on multisubject neuroimaging (electroencephalography) data to study the effects on the functional states of the frontal cortex and parietal lobe for chronic exposure of alcohol.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Assessing malaria using neutral zone classifiers with mixture discriminant analysis on 2D images of red blood cells</title>
      <link>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/mohammed2019assessing/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/mohammed2019assessing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Journal of Biostatistics and Epidemiology&lt;/em&gt; (2019).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Background and Aim: We aim to build a classifier to distinguish between malaria-infected red blood cells (RBCs) and healthy cells using the two-dimensional (2D) microscopic images of RBCs. We demonstrate the process of cell segmentation and feature extraction from the 2D images.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Methods and Materials: We describe an approach to address the problem using mixture discriminant analysis (MDA) on the 2D image profiles of the RBCs. The extracted features are used with Gaussian MDA to distinguish between healthy and malaria infected cells. We also use the neutral zone classifiers where ambiguous cases are identified separately by the classifier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Results: We compare the classification results from the regular classifiers such as linear discriminant analysis (LDA) or MDA and the methods where neutral zone classifiers are used. We see that including the neutral zone improves the classification results by controlling the false positive and false negatives. The number of misclassifications are seen to be lower than the case without neutral zone classifiers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conclusion: This paper presents an alternative approach for classification by incorporating neutral zone classifier approach, where a prediction is not made for the ambiguous cases. From the data analysis we see that this approach based on neutral zone classifiers presents a useful alternative in classification problems for various applications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data Visualization with R Shiny</title>
      <link>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/teaching/uconnrshiny/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/teaching/uconnrshiny/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This workshop was conducted by the &lt;a href=&#34;https://stat.uconn.edu/consulting-info/&#34;&gt;Statistical Consulting Services&lt;/a&gt; in the Department of Statistics at the University of Connecticut in April 2018.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>STAT 3025 - Statistical Methods (Calculus Level II)</title>
      <link>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/teaching/stat3025-fall/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/teaching/stat3025-fall/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>STAT 3025 - Statistical Methods (Calculus Level II)</title>
      <link>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/teaching/stat3025-summer/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/teaching/stat3025-summer/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Teaching Assistant</title>
      <link>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/teaching/ta/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 May 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/teaching/ta/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Introduction to Statistics I &amp;amp; II - Department of Statistics, University of Connecticut&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Introduction to Mathematical  Statistics I &amp;amp; II - Department of Statistics, University of Connecticut&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Numerical Linear Algebra - Chennai Mathematical Institute&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Probability Theory - Chennai Mathematical Institute&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A dynamical systems approach to systemic risk in a financial network</title>
      <link>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/bhat2016dynamical/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/bhat2016dynamical/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In &lt;em&gt;2016 Indian Control Conference (ICC)&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The insolvency of a financial entity such as a bank can trigger a sequence of defaults in a network of financial entities interconnected through mutual financial obligations, thus posing a systemic risk to all the financial entities that make up the network. This paper studies the well-known Eisenberg-Noe model for systemic risk from a dynamical systems perspective. In particular, we model the sequence of defaults in the form of a dynamical system, and provide results on its stability and asymptotic behavior.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/awards_service/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/awards_service/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;awards&#34;&gt;Awards&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;BU SPH Early Career Catalyst Award&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Precision Health Scholars Award - University of Michigan&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;At University of Connecticut
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Doctoral Dissertation Fellowship&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Doctoral Student Travel Award&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Predoctoral Dissertation Fellowship&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Matthew M. Goldstein Graduate Fellowship&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Multiple conference travel grants&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Chennai Mathematical Institute Medal of Excellence&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;INSPIRE Scholarship for Higher Education (2009-2014) - Ministry of Science &amp;amp; Technology, Government of India&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;service&#34;&gt;Service&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;reviewer&#34;&gt;Reviewer&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Annals of Applied Statistics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Biometrics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Biostatistics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Clinical Cancer Informatics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Harvard Data Science Review&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Journal of the American Heart Association&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Journal of the American Medical Informatics Association&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Spatial Statistics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;STAT&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;professional-societies&#34;&gt;Professional Societies&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;International Indian Statistical Association (IISA)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;International Society for Bayesian Analysis (ISBA)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;New England Statistical Society (NESS)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;American Statistical Association (ASA)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;International Biometric Society: Eastern North American Region (ENAR)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;organizer-invited-sessions&#34;&gt;Organizer (Invited Sessions)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;International Indian Statistical Association Annual Conference 2022&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Joint Statistical Meetings 2022&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;New England Statistics Symposium 2022&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Joint Statistical Meetings 2021&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ENAR Spring Meeting 2021&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Joint Statistical Meetings 2020&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;leadership-roles&#34;&gt;Leadership Roles&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Founding Co-Organizer&lt;/em&gt;, IISA Statistics and Data Science Innovations Webinar Series&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Co-Organizer&lt;/em&gt;, Biostatistics Department Seminar, Boston University&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Member&lt;/em&gt;, IISA Membership &amp;amp; Outreach Committee&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;previous&#34;&gt;Previous&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Executive Committee Member&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Statistics Graduate Student Committee, University of Connecticut&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tarang (South Asian cultural organisation), University of Connecticut&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Student Committee Member&lt;/em&gt;, 31st New England Statistics Symposium, University of Connecticut&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Senator&lt;/em&gt;, UConn Graduate Student Senate, University of Connecticut&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Member&lt;/em&gt;, Faculty Standards Committee, University of Connecticut Senate&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Talks</title>
      <link>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/talks/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/talks/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Classification of high-dimensional electroencephalography data with location selection using structured spike-and-slab prior&lt;/em&gt; (Poster)
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Joint Statistical Meetings 2022, Washington, DC &lt;em&gt;August 2022&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Density-based classification in diabetic retinopathy through thickness of retinal layers from optical coherence tomography&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Joint Statistical Meetings 2022, Washington, DC &lt;em&gt;August 2022&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Quantifying T2-FLAIR Mismatch in Gliomas Using Geographically Weighted Regression and Density Functions&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;22nd Meeting of New Researchers in Statistics and Probability, George Mason University, Fairfax, Virginia &lt;em&gt;August 2022&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;35th New England Statistics Symposium, UConn &lt;em&gt;May 2022&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Statistical methods for biomedical imaging and digital data analysis&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;BU Biostatistics Research Blitz, Boston, Massachusetts &lt;em&gt;March 2022&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Layered variable selection for multivariate Bayesian regression: A case study in imaging genomics&lt;/em&gt; (Alternate title: Tumor radiogenomics with Bayesian layered variable selection)
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;BU Epidemiology Seminar, Boston, Massachusetts &lt;em&gt;March 2022&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Joint Statistical Meetings 2021 - Virtual. &lt;em&gt;August 2021&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ENAR Spring Meeting - Virtual. &lt;em&gt;March 2021&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Computational Biostatistics and Biomedical Imaging Data Analysis&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tech Talks 1.0 by Student&amp;rsquo;s Association of Artificial Intelligence and Data Science, G H Raisoni College of Engineering and Management, Pune, India - Virtual &lt;em&gt;February 2022&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;RADIOHEAD: Radiogenomic analysis incorporating tumor heterogeneity in imaging through densities&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Fifth Eastern Asia Chapter&amp;ndash;The International Society for Bayesian Analysis Conference: A Satellite Meeting of the 2020 ISBA World Meeting to Celebrate James O Berger&amp;rsquo;s 70th Birthday&amp;quot; - Virtual &lt;em&gt;November 2021&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Biostatistics Student Association Seminar, Boston, Massachusetts &lt;em&gt;November 2021&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Center for Computational Mathematics Seminar, Flatiron Institute, Simons Foundation, New York - Virtual &lt;em&gt;June 2021&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Statistical Methods in Imaging Conference - Virtual. &lt;em&gt;May 2021&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2020 University of Michigan Precision Health Symposium - Virtual. (Poster) &lt;em&gt;August 2020&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Joint Statistical Meetings 2020 - Virtual. &lt;em&gt;August 2020&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ENAR Spring Meeting, Nashville, Tennessee. &lt;em&gt;March 2020&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;IISA Annual Conference, Mumbai, India. &lt;em&gt;December 2019&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Biostatistics Career Development panel discussion on &amp;lsquo;Academic Career Path&amp;rsquo;&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Department of Biostatistics, Boston University, Boston. &lt;em&gt;October 2021&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Density-based classification using images: Application to diabetic retinopathy&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Precision Health Seminar (Pharmacy 217), University of Michigan-Ann Arbor. &lt;em&gt;February 2021&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;StatChat 2020: Panel discussions with undergraduate and masters students on career and academic perspectives in statistics and data science&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;NMIMS Sunandan Divatia School of Science - Virtual. &lt;em&gt;August &amp;amp; September 2020&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Understanding COVID-19 dynamics via individual-level temporal and network modeling: Lessons from India and China&lt;/em&gt; (joint presentation with Dr. Zhenke Wu, Rupam Bhattacharyya and Dr. Veerabhadran Baladandayuthapani)
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;MIDAS COVID-19 Special Seminar Series, University of Michigan-Ann Arbor. &lt;em&gt;June 2020&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Integrative statistical modeling approaches for imaging-genomics data&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Precision Health Seminar (Pharmacy 217), University of Michigan-Ann Arbor. &lt;em&gt;March 2020&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tools and Technology Seminar, University of Michigan-Ann Arbor. &lt;em&gt;March 2020&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bayesian variable selection using spike-and-slab prior with application to high-dimensional EEG data&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ENAR Spring Meeting, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania. &lt;em&gt;March 2019&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Joint Statistical Meetings, Vancouver, Canada. &lt;em&gt;July 2018&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Symposium on Data Science and Statistics, Reston, Virginia. &lt;em&gt;May 2018&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;BayesComp 2018, Barcelona, Spain. (Poster) &lt;em&gt;March 2018&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;IISA Annual Conference, Hyderabad, India. &lt;em&gt;December 2017&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;34th Quality and Productivity Research Conference, University of Connecticut. (Poster) &lt;em&gt;June 2017&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Modeling of large insurance claims and occurrence data&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;31st New England Statistics Symposium, University of Connecticut. &lt;em&gt;April 2017&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
