<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Yuping Zhang | Shariq Mohammed</title>
    <link>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/authors/yuping-zhang/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/authors/yuping-zhang/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Yuping Zhang</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 28 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>Yuping Zhang</title>
      <link>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/authors/yuping-zhang/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Classification of high-dimensional electroencephalography data with location selection using structured spike-and-slab prior</title>
      <link>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/mohammed2020classification/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/mohammed2020classification/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Invited for Statistical Analysis and Data Mining Best Paper Session at Joint Statistical Meetings 2022.&lt;/strong&gt; (&lt;a href=&#34;https://ww2.amstat.org/meetings/jsm/2022/onlineprogram/ActivityDetails.cfm?SessionID=221965&#34;&gt;JSM 2022 Program&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Statistical Analysis and Data Mining: The ASA Data Science Journal&lt;/em&gt; (2020).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the advent of modern technologies, it is increasingly common to deal with data of large dimensions in various scientific fields of study. In this paper, we develop a Bayesian approach for the classification of multi-subject high-dimensional electroencephalography (EEG) data. In this EEG data, we have a matrix of covariates corresponding to each subject from either the alcoholic or control group. The matrix covariates have a natural spatial correlation based on the locations of the brain, and temporal correlation as the measurements are taken over time. We employ a divide and conquer strategy by building multiple local Bayesian models at each time point separately. We incorporate the spatial structure through the structured spike-and-slab prior, which has inherent variable selection properties. The temporal structure is incorporated within the prior by learning from the local model from the previous time point. We pool the information from the local models and use a weighted average to design a prediction method. We perform simulation studies to show the efficiency of our approach and demonstrate the local Bayesian modeling with a case study on EEG data.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bayesian variable selection using spike-and-slab priors with application to high dimensional electroencephalography data by local modelling</title>
      <link>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/mohammed2019bayesian/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/mohammed2019bayesian/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Journal of the Royal Statistical Society: Series C (Applied Statistics)&lt;/em&gt; (2019).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because of the immense technological advances, very often we encounter data in high dimensions. Any set of measurements taken at multiple time points for multiple subjects leads to data of more than two dimensions (a matrix of covariates for each subject). We present a Bayesian variable‐selection method to identify the active regions in the brain as a response to a certain stimulus. We build binary classification models of subject level responses by using binary regression with Gaussian models on the latent variables. We also study the scaled normal priors on the latent variables, as they cover a large family of distributions. We use continuous spike‐and‐slab priors to incorporate variable selection within the modelling. Because of the computational complexity, we build many local (at different time points) models and make predictions by utilizing the temporal structure between the local models. We perform two‐stage variable selection for each of these local models. We demonstrate the effectiveness of such modelling through the results of a simulation study. We then present the performance of these models on multisubject neuroimaging (electroencephalography) data to study the effects on the functional states of the frontal cortex and parietal lobe for chronic exposure of alcohol. &lt;a href=&#34;https://academic.oup.com/jrsssc/article/68/5/1305/7058603&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
