<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Selected Journal Articles | Shariq Mohammed</title>
    <link>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/tags/selected-journal-articles/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/tags/selected-journal-articles/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Selected Journal Articles</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 03 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>Selected Journal Articles</title>
      <link>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/tags/selected-journal-articles/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quantifying T2-FLAIR mismatch using geographically weighted regression and predicting molecular status in lower-grade gliomas</title>
      <link>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/mohammed2021quantifying/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/mohammed2021quantifying/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;American Journal of Neuroradiology&lt;/em&gt; (2021). &lt;em&gt;(Just Accepted)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Background and Purpose&lt;/em&gt;. T2-FLAIR mismatch sign is a validated imaging sign of IDH-mutant 1p/19q non-codeleted gliomas. It is identified by radiologists through visual inspection of pre-operative MRI scans, and has been shown to identify IDH-mutant 1p/19q non-codeleted gliomas with high positive predictive value. We have developed an approach to quantify the T2-FLAIR mismatch signature, and use it to predict molecular status of lower-grade gliomas (LGG).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Materials and Methods&lt;/em&gt;. We used multi-parametric MRI scans and segmentation labels of 108 pre-operative LGG tumors from The Cancer Imaging Archive. Clinical information and T2-FLAIR mismatch sign labels were obtained from supplementary material of relevant publications. We adopted an objective analytical approach to estimate this sign through a geographically weighted regression (GWR), and use the residuals for each case to construct a probability density function (serving as residual signature). These functions are then analyzed using an appropriate statistical framework.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Results&lt;/em&gt;. We observe statistically significant (p-value = 0.05) differences between the averages of residual signatures for IDH-mutated 1p/19q non-codeleted class of tumors versus other categories. Our classifier predicts these cases with area under the curve (AUC) of 0.98, high specificity and sensitivity. It also predicts T2-FLAIR mismatch sign within these cases with an AUC of 0.93.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Conclusions&lt;/em&gt;. Based on this retrospective study, we show that GWR-based residual signatures are highly informative of T2-FLAIR mismatch sign, and can identify IDH mutation and 1p/19q codeletion status with high predictive power. The utility of proposed quantification of T2-FLAIR mismatch sign can be potentially validated through a prospective multi-institutional study.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Spatial Tweedie exponential dispersion models: An application to insurance rate-making</title>
      <link>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/halder2020spatial/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/halder2020spatial/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Scandinavian Actuarial Journal&lt;/em&gt; (2021). &lt;em&gt;(Just Accepted)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this paper we propose a statistical modeling framework that contributes to advancing methods for modeling insurance policy premium in the actuarial literature. Specification of separate frequency and severity models, accounting for territorial risk and performing accurate inference are some of the challenges actuaries face while modeling policy premium. We focus on building a methodology that builds parsimonious and interpretable models for modeling policy premium. Policy premiums are characterized to follow a semi-continuous probability distribution, featuring a non-zero probability mass at zero along with a positive continuous support. Interpretability is a concern when quantifying risks that policy premium face from spatial variation. Risk conferred from spatial sources is often treated as an unobserved. Commonly used strategies in the literature are known to successfully quantify the variation, but do not necessarily produce interpretable estimates. Furthermore, resorting to two-part frequency-severity models leaves the actuary indecisive about the specification of covariates and spatial effects. The proposed methods in the paper considers a more parsimonious approach by resorting to zero-adjusted models for policy premium, that models both the mean policy-premium and the associated dispersion around the mean. Quantification of variation from spatial sources is proposed for the mean model. Allowing for a non-constant dispersion across observations results in a better estimate of the underlying variability, producing superior estimates for coefficients. The novelty of the proposed approach lies in the framework developed, that allows for joint estimation of effect of policy or individual characteristics on both the mean policy premium and dispersion, while quantifying spatial variability in the mean model. The developed methods are applied to a database featuring policy premiums arising from the collision coverage in insurance policies for motor vehicles within the state of Connecticut, USA for the year 2008.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>RADIOHEAD: Radiogenomic analysis incorporating tumor heterogeneity in imagine through densities</title>
      <link>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/mohammed2021radiohead/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/mohammed2021radiohead/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Annals of Applied Statistics&lt;/em&gt; (2021). &lt;em&gt;(Just Accepted)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recent technological advancements have enabled detailed investigation of associations between the molecular architecture and tumor heterogeneity, through multi-source integration of radiological imaging and genomic (radiogenomic) data. In this paper, we integrate and harness radiogenomic data in patients with lower grade gliomas (LGG), a type of brain cancer, in order to develop a regression framework called RADIOHEAD (RADIOgenomic analysis incorporating tumor HEterogeneity in imAging through Densities) to identify radiogenomic associations. Imaging data is represented through voxel intensity probability density functions of tumor sub-regions obtained from multimodal magnetic resonance imaging, and genomic data through molecular signatures in the form of pathway enrichment scores corresponding to their gene expression profiles. Employing a Riemannian-geometric framework for principal component analysis on the set of probability densities functions, we map each probability density to a vector of principal component scores, which are then included as predictors in a Bayesian regression model with the pathway enrichment scores as the response. Variable selection compatible with the grouping structure amongst the predictors induced through the tumor sub-regions is carried out under a group spike-and-slab prior. A Bayesian false discovery rate mechanism is then used to infer significant associations based on the posterior distribution of the regression coefficients. Our analyses reveal several pathways relevant to LGG etiology (such as synaptic transmission, nerve impulse and neurotransmitter pathways), to have significant associations with the corresponding imaging-based predictors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Scalable spatio-temporal Bayesian analysis of high-dimensional electroencephalography data</title>
      <link>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/mohammed2021scalable/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/mohammed2021scalable/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Canadian Journal of Statistics&lt;/em&gt; (2021).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We present a scalable Bayesian modeling approach for identifying brain regions that respond to a certain stimulus and use them to classify subjects. We specifically deal with multi-subject electroencephalography (EEG) data with a binary response distinguishing between alcoholic and control groups. The covariates are matrix-variate with measurements taken for each subject at different locations across multiple time points. EEG data has a complex structure with both spatial and temporal attributes to it. We use a divide-and-conquer strategy to build multiple local models, that is, one model at each time point separately. We employ Bayesian variable selection approaches using a structured continuous spike-and-slab prior to identify the locations which respond to a certain stimulus. We incorporate the spatio-temporal structure through a Kronecker product of the spatial and temporal correlation matrices. We develop a highly scalable estimation algorithm using likelihood approximation to deal with large number of parameters in the model. Variable selection is done via clustering of the locations based on their duration of activation. We use scoring rules to evaluate the prediction performance. We perform simulation studies to demonstrate the efficiency of our scalable algorithm in terms of estimation and fast computation. We present results using our scalable approach for a case study on multi-subject EEG data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Density-based classification in diabetic retinopathy through thickness of retinal layers from optical coherence tomography</title>
      <link>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/mohammed2020density/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/mohammed2020density/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Scientific Reports&lt;/em&gt; (2020).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Diabetic retinopathy (DR) is a severe retinal disorder that can lead to vision loss, however, its underlying mechanism has not been fully understood. Previous studies have taken advantage of Optical Coherence Tomography (OCT) and shown that the thickness of individual retinal layers are affected in patients with DR. However, most studies analyzed the thickness by calculating summary statistics from retinal thickness maps of the macula region. This study aims to apply a density function-based statistical framework to the thickness data obtained through OCT, and to compare the predictive power of various retinal layers to assess the severity of DR. We used a prototype data set of 107 subjects which are comprised of 38 non-proliferative DR (NPDR), 28 without DR (NoDR), and 41 controls. Based on the thickness profiles, we constructed novel features which capture the variation in the distribution of the pixel-wise retinal layer thicknesses from OCT. We quantified the predictive power of each of the retinal layers to distinguish between all three pairwise comparisons of the severity in DR (NoDR vs NPDR, controls vs NPDR and controls vs NoDR). When applied to this preliminary DR data set, our density-based method demonstrated better predictive results compared with simple summary statistics. Furthermore, our results indicate considerable differences in retinal layer structuring based on the severity of DR. We found that: (a) the outer plexiform layer is the most discriminative layer for classifying NoDR vs NPDR; (b) the outer plexiform, inner nuclear and ganglion cell layers are the strongest biomarkers for discriminating controls from NPDR; and (c) the inner nuclear layer distinguishes best between controls and NoDR.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
