<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>3 | Shariq Mohammed</title>
    <link>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication_types/3/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication_types/3/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>3</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 20 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>3</title>
      <link>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication_types/3/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Network-based Modeling of COVID-19 Dynamics: Early Pandemic Spread in India</title>
      <link>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/bhattacharyya2021network/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/bhattacharyya2021network/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Modeling the dynamics of COVID-19 pandemic spread is a challenging and relevant problem. Established models for the epidemic spread such as compartmental epidemiological models e.g. Susceptible-Infected-Recovered (SIR) models and its variants, have been discussed extensively in the literature and utilized to forecast the growth of the pandemic across different hot-spots in the world. The standard formulations of SIR models rely upon summary-level data, which may not be able to fully capture the complete dynamics of the pandemic growth. Since the disease spreads from carriers to susceptible individuals via some form of contact, it inherently relies upon a network of individuals for its growth, with edges established via direct interaction, such as shared physical proximity. Using individual-level COVID-19 data from the early days (January 30 to April 15, 2020) of the pandemic in India, and under a network-based SIR model framework, we performed state-specific forecasting under multiple scenarios characterized by the basic reproduction number of COVID-19 across 34 Indian states and union territories. We validated our short-term projections using observed case counts and the long-term projections using national sero-survey findings. Based on healthcare availability data, we also performed projections to assess the burdens on the infrastructure along the spectrum of the pandemic growth. We have developed an interactive dashboard summarizing our results. Our predictions successfully identified the initial hot-spots of India such as Maharashtra and Delhi, and those that emerged later, such as Madhya Pradesh and Kerala. These models have the potential to inform appropriate policies for isolation and mitigation strategies to contain the pandemic, through a phased approach by appropriate resource prioritization and allocation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Integrative Bayesian models using post-selective inference: a case study in radiogenomics</title>
      <link>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/panigrahi2020integrative/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/panigrahi2020integrative/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Identifying direct links between gene pathways and clinical endpoints for highly fatal diseases such as cancer is a formidable task. Integrative analyses play a crucial role in modeling these links by relying upon associations between a wealth of intermediary variables and genomic measurements. Motivated to harness phenotypic information about tumors towards a molecular characterization of low-grade gliomas, we develop a data driven Bayesian framework to define sharp models, and calibrate accurately and efficiently uncertainties associated with the promising biological findings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Bayesian methods we propose in the article (i) are amenable to a flexible class of adaptive models, determined via a complex interplay between signals sifted from variable selection algorithms and domain specific knowledge; (ii) have the advantage of computationally efficient high dimensional inference due to a focus on sharp models with fewer parameters, when compared to their non-adaptive counterparts; (iii) exhibit a significantly better reconciliation between model adaptivity and inferential power than state-of-art approaches, when constrained by the curse of dimensionality. Our main workforce involves a carefully constructed conditional likelihood and utilizes a reparameterization map to obtain compact formulae for a selection-corrected posterior. Deploying our methods to investigate radiogenomic characteristics for diffuse low-grade gliomas, we successfully uncover associations between several biologically important gene pathways and patient survival times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Spatial risk estimation in Tweedie compound Poisson double generalized linear models</title>
      <link>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/halder2019spatial/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/halder2019spatial/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tweedie exponential dispersion family constitutes a fairly rich sub-class of the celebrated exponential family. In particular, a member, compound Poisson gamma (CP-g) model has seen extensive use over the past decade for modeling mixed response featuring exact zeros with a continuous response from a gamma distribution. This paper proposes a framework to perform residual analysis on CP-g double generalized linear models for spatial uncertainty quantification. Approximations are introduced to proposed framework making the procedure scalable, without compromise in accuracy of estimation and model complexity; accompanied by sensitivity analysis to model mis-specification. Proposed framework is applied to modeling spatial uncertainty in insurance loss costs arising from automobile collision coverage. Scalability is demonstrated by choosing sizable spatial reference domains comprised of groups of states within the United States of America.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Spatial Tweedie exponential dispersion models</title>
      <link>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/halder2020spatial/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/halder2020spatial/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This paper proposes a general modeling framework that allows for uncertainty quantification at the individual covariate level and spatial referencing, operating withing a double generalized linear model (DGLM). DGLMs provide a general modeling framework allowing dispersion to depend in a link-linear fashion on chosen covariates. We focus on working with Tweedie exponential dispersion models while considering DGLMs, the reason being their recent wide-spread use for modeling mixed response types. Adopting a regularization based approach, we suggest a class of flexible convex penalties derived from an un-directed graph that facilitates estimation of the unobserved spatial effect. Developments are concisely showcased by proposing a co-ordinate descent algorithm that jointly explains variation from covariates in mean and dispersion through estimation of respective model coefficients while estimating the unobserved spatial effect. Simulations performed show that proposed approach is superior to competitors like the ridge and un-penalized versions. Finally, a real data application is considered while modeling insurance losses arising from automobile collisions in the state of Connecticut, USA for the year 2008.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
