<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Snigdha Panigrahi | Shariq Mohammed</title>
    <link>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/authors/snigdha-panigrahi/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/authors/snigdha-panigrahi/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Snigdha Panigrahi</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 02 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>Snigdha Panigrahi</title>
      <link>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/authors/snigdha-panigrahi/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Integrative Bayesian models using post-selective inference: a case study in radiogenomics</title>
      <link>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/panigrahi2020integrative/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/panigrahi2020integrative/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Biometrics (Just Accepted)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Identifying direct links between gene pathways and clinical endpoints for highly fatal diseases such as cancer is a formidable task. Integrative analyses play a crucial role in modeling these links by relying upon associations between a wealth of intermediary variables and genomic measurements. Motivated to harness phenotypic information about tumors towards a molecular characterization of low-grade gliomas, we develop a data driven Bayesian framework to define sharp models, and calibrate accurately and efficiently uncertainties associated with the promising biological findings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Bayesian methods we propose in the article (i) are amenable to a flexible class of adaptive models, determined via a complex interplay between signals sifted from variable selection algorithms and domain specific knowledge; (ii) have the advantage of computationally efficient high dimensional inference due to a focus on sharp models with fewer parameters, when compared to their non-adaptive counterparts; (iii) exhibit a significantly better reconciliation between model adaptivity and inferential power than state-of-art approaches, when constrained by the curse of dimensionality. Our main workforce involves a carefully constructed conditional likelihood and utilizes a reparameterization map to obtain compact formulae for a selection-corrected posterior. Deploying our methods to investigate radiogenomic characteristics for diffuse low-grade gliomas, we successfully uncover associations between several biologically important gene pathways and patient survival times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
