<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>John Kim | Shariq Mohammed</title>
    <link>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/authors/john-kim/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/authors/john-kim/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>John Kim</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 01 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>John Kim</title>
      <link>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/authors/john-kim/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Comparative study of radiologists vs machine learning in differentiating biopsy-proven pseudoprogression and true progression in diffuse gliomas</title>
      <link>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/turk2022comparative/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/turk2022comparative/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Neuroscience Informatics&lt;/em&gt; (2022).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Background and Purpose&lt;/strong&gt; MRI features of tumor progression and
pseudoprogression may be indistinguishable especially without enhancing
portion of the diffuse gliomas. Our aim is to discriminate these two
conditions using radiomics and machine learning algorithm and to compare
them with human observations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Materials and Methods&lt;/strong&gt; Three consecutive MRI studies before a
definitive biopsy in 43 diffuse glioma patients (7 pseudoprogression and
36 true progression cases) who underwent treatment were evaluated. Two
neuroradiologists reviewed pre- and post-contrast T1, T2, FLAIR, ADC,
rCBV, rCBF, K2, and MTT maps. Patterns of enhancement, ADC maps, rCBV,
rCBF, MTT, K2 values, and perilesional FLAIR signal intensity changes
were recorded. Odds ratios (OR) for each descriptor, raters&#39; success in
predicting true and pseudoprogression, and inter-observer reliability
were calculated using the R statistics software. Unpaired Student&amp;rsquo;s
t-test and receiver operating characteristic (ROC) analysis were applied
to compare the texture parameters and histogram analysis of pseudo- and
true progression groups. All first-order and second-order image texture
features and shape features were used to train and test the Random
Forest classifier (RFC). Observers&#39; success and RFC were compared.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Results&lt;/strong&gt; Observers could not identify true progression in the first
visit. However, accuracy of the RFC model was 81%. For the second and
third visits, the rater&amp;rsquo;s success of prediction was between 62% and 72%.
The accuracy for the second and last visit with RFC was 75% and 81%.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusions&lt;/strong&gt; Random Forest classifier was more successful than human
observations in predicting pseudoprogression using MRI.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Discriminating pseudoprogression and true progression in diffuse infiltrating glioma using multi-parametric MRI data through deep learning</title>
      <link>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/lee2020discriminating/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/lee2020discriminating/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Scientific Reports&lt;/em&gt; (2020).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Differentiating pseudoprogression from true tumor progression has become a significant challenge in follow-up of diffuse infiltrating gliomas, particularly high grade, which leads to a potential treatment delay for patients with early glioma recurrence. In this study, we proposed to use a multiparametric MRI data as a sequence input for the convolutional neural network with the recurrent neural network based deep learning structure to discriminate between pseudoprogression and true tumor progression. In this study, 43 biopsy-proven patient data identified as diffuse infiltrating glioma patients whose disease progressed/recurred were used. The dataset consists of five original MRI sequences; pre-contrast T1-weighted, post-contrast T1-weighted, T2-weighted, FLAIR, and ADC images as well as two engineered sequences; T1post–T1pre and T2–FLAIR. Next, we used three CNN-LSTM models with a different set of sequences as input sequences to pass through CNN-LSTM layers. We performed threefold cross-validation in the training dataset and generated the boxplot, accuracy, and ROC curve, AUC from each trained model with the test dataset to evaluate models. The mean accuracy for VGG16 models ranged from 0.44 to 0.60 and the mean AUC ranged from 0.47 to 0.59. For CNN-LSTM model, the mean accuracy ranged from 0.62 to 0.75 and the mean AUC ranged from 0.64 to 0.81. The performance of the proposed CNN-LSTM with multiparametric sequence data was found to outperform the popular convolutional CNN with a single MRI sequence. In conclusion, incorporating all available MRI sequences into a sequence input for a CNN-LSTM model improved diagnostic performance for discriminating between pseudoprogression and true tumor progression.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
