<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Michael LaValley | Shariq Mohammed</title>
    <link>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/authors/michael-lavalley/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/authors/michael-lavalley/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Michael LaValley</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>Michael LaValley</title>
      <link>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/authors/michael-lavalley/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>A national growth mixture modeling analysis of county-level COVID-19 incidence rate trajectories and health inequities during three successive pandemic waves in 2020</title>
      <link>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/dukes2025national/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/dukes2025national/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Scientific Reports&lt;/em&gt; (2025).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We applied Growth Mixture Modeling (GMM) to characterize county-level COVID-19 incidence rate (IR) trajectories across three distinct waves in the United States from March 15 to November 2, 2020. GMM enabled the identification of latent subpopulations with shared temporal patterns of disease spread, offering a flexible analytic framework for uncovering both known and evolving disparities. Across the three periods, up to five trajectory groups were identified, revealing substantial geographic and temporal heterogeneity. To support interpretation and reduce multiple comparisons, we developed and validated a 17-item Social Determinants of Health (SDOH) index representing county-level economic and resource access factors. Higher-incidence rate trajectories consistently aligned with lower SDOH scores and greater proportions of Black or African American residents and younger populations. These disparities shifted over time, with patterns of high-incidence rates emerging in resource-limited counties across the South and Midwest in later waves. By further assessing well-documented inequities and expanding understanding of their dynamic expression across space and time, this study demonstrates the utility of GMM for public health surveillance, planning, and equitable response strategies in future outbreaks.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Modeling health and well-being measures using ZIP code spatial neighborhood patterns</title>
      <link>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/jain2024modeling/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/jain2024modeling/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Scientific Reports&lt;/em&gt; (2024).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Individual-level assessment of health and well-being permits analysis of community well-being and health risk evaluations across several dimensions of health. It also enables comparison and rankings of reported health and well-being for large geographical areas such as states, metropolitan areas, and counties. However, there is large variation in reported well-being within such large spatial units underscoring the importance of analyzing well-being at more granular levels, such as ZIP codes. In this paper, we model well-being data to generate ZIP code tabulation area (ZCTA)-level rankings through spatially informed statistical modeling. We build regression models for individual-level overall well-being index and scores from five subscales (Physical, Financial, Social, Community, Purpose) using individual-level demographic characteristics as predictors while including a ZCTA-level spatial effect using a graph Laplacian. Deployed on data from Massachusetts and Georgia, the model captures demographic effects and yields spatial effect estimates for all ZCTAs (including some without observations), enabling community‑level rankings.  &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
