<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Preprints | Shariq Mohammed</title>
    <link>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/tags/preprints/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/tags/preprints/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Preprints</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 21 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>Preprints</title>
      <link>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/tags/preprints/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tumor radiogenomics with Bayesian layered variable selection</title>
      <link>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/mohammed2021tumor/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/mohammed2021tumor/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We propose a statistical framework to integrate radiological magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) and genomic data to identify the underlying radiogenomic associations in lower grade gliomas (LGG). We devise a novel imaging phenotype by dividing the tumor region into concentric spherical layers that mimics the tumor evolution process. MRI data within each layer is represented by voxel&amp;ndash;intensity-based probability density functions which capture the complete information about tumor heterogeneity. Under a Riemannian-geometric framework these densities are mapped to a vector of principal component scores which act as imaging phenotypes. Subsequently, we build Bayesian variable selection models for each layer with the imaging phenotypes as the response and the genomic markers as predictors. Our novel hierarchical prior formulation incorporates the interior-to-exterior structure of the layers, and the correlation between the genomic markers. We employ a computationally-efficient Expectation&amp;ndash;Maximization-based strategy for estimation. Simulation studies demonstrate the superior performance of our approach compared to other approaches. With a focus on the cancer driver genes in LGG, we discuss some biologically relevant findings. Genes implicated with survival and oncogenesis are identified as being associated with the spherical layers, which could potentially serve as early-stage diagnostic markers for disease monitoring, prior to routine invasive approaches.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Spatial risk estimation in Tweedie compound Poisson double generalized linear models</title>
      <link>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/halder2019spatial/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/halder2019spatial/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tweedie exponential dispersion family constitutes a fairly rich sub-class of the celebrated exponential family. In particular, a member, compound Poisson gamma (CP-g) model has seen extensive use over the past decade for modeling mixed response featuring exact zeros with a continuous response from a gamma distribution. This paper proposes a framework to perform residual analysis on CP-g double generalized linear models for spatial uncertainty quantification. Approximations are introduced to proposed framework making the procedure scalable, without compromise in accuracy of estimation and model complexity; accompanied by sensitivity analysis to model mis-specification. Proposed framework is applied to modeling spatial uncertainty in insurance loss costs arising from automobile collision coverage. Scalability is demonstrated by choosing sizable spatial reference domains comprised of groups of states within the United States of America.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
