<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Jack E. Pohlmann | Shariq Mohammed</title>
    <link>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/authors/jack-e.-pohlmann/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/authors/jack-e.-pohlmann/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Jack E. Pohlmann</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 05 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>Jack E. Pohlmann</title>
      <link>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/authors/jack-e.-pohlmann/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Later midline shift is associated with better post-hospitalization discharge status after large middle cerebral artery stroke</title>
      <link>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/song2025later/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/song2025later/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Scientific Reports&lt;/em&gt; (2025).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Space occupying cerebral edema is a feared complication after large ischemic stroke, occurring in up to 30% of patients with middle cerebral artery (MCA) occlusion and peaking 2–4 days after injury. Little is known about the factors and outcomes associated with peak edema timing, especially after 96 h. We aimed to characterize differences and compare discharge status between patients who experienced maximum midline shift (MLS) or decompressive hemicraniectomy (DHC) in the acute (&amp;lt; 48 h), average (48–96 h), and subacute (&amp;gt; 96 h) groups. We performed a two-center, retrospective study of patients with ≥ 1/2 MCA territory infarct and MLS. We constructed a multivariable model to test the association of subacute peak edema and favorable discharge status, adjusting for various confounders. Of 321 eligible patients, 32%, 36%, and 32% experienced acute, average, and subacute peak edema. Subacute peak edema was significantly associated with higher odds of favorable discharge than acute peak edema (aOR, 2.05; 95% CI, 1.03–4.11). Subacute peak edema after large MCA stroke is associated with better discharge status compared to acute peak edema courses. Understanding how the timing of cerebral edema affects risk of unfavorable discharge has important implications for treatment decisions and prognostication.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quantitative Pupillometry Predicts Neurologic Deterioration in Patients with Large Middle Cerebral Artery Stroke</title>
      <link>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/du2025quantitative/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 19 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/du2025quantitative/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Annals of Neurology&lt;/em&gt; (2025).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Objective: This study assesses whether longitudinal quantitative pupillometry predicts neurological deterioration after large middle cerebral artery (MCA) stroke and determines how early changes are detectable. Methods: This prospective, single‑center observational cohort study included patients with large MCA stroke admitted to Boston Medical Center’s intensive care unit (2019–2024). Associations between time‑to‑neurologic deterioration and quantitative pupillometry, including Neurological Pupil Index (NPi), were assessed using Cox proportional hazards models with time‑dependent covariates adjusted for age, sex, and Alberta Stroke Program Early CT Score. Models using dilation velocity were compared with partial likelihood ratio tests. Pupillometric changes over 2‑hour intervals in the 12 hours preceding deterioration were analyzed with linear mixed‑effects modeling and Tukey’s test. Matched referents were used for comparison. Results: Among 71 patients, 32 (45.1%) experienced deterioration. A 1‑unit decrease in NPi was associated with higher hazard of deterioration (HR 2.46; 95% CI 1.68–3.61). Dilation velocity improved model performance compared to NPi alone. NPi was significantly lower at 0–2 and 2–4 hours before deterioration compared to 10–12 hours prior. Interpretation: Quantitative pupillometry predicts neurological deterioration in MCA stroke, with declines detectable up to 12 hours prior; dilation velocity shows promise as a biomarker.  &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quantitative Pupillometry Post‑Surgical Decompression Predicts Severe Neurologic Disability in Patients with Acute Brain Injury</title>
      <link>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/mallinger2024quantitative/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/mallinger2024quantitative/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Neurocritical Care Society Annual Meeting&lt;/em&gt; (2024).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Accepted as a poster at the conference.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
