<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Arvind Rao | Shariq Mohammed</title>
    <link>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/authors/arvind-rao/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/authors/arvind-rao/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Arvind Rao</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 02 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>Arvind Rao</title>
      <link>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/authors/arvind-rao/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Integrative Bayesian models using post-selective inference: a case study in radiogenomics</title>
      <link>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/panigrahi2020integrative/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/panigrahi2020integrative/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Biometrics (Just Accepted)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Identifying direct links between gene pathways and clinical endpoints for highly fatal diseases such as cancer is a formidable task. Integrative analyses play a crucial role in modeling these links by relying upon associations between a wealth of intermediary variables and genomic measurements. Motivated to harness phenotypic information about tumors towards a molecular characterization of low-grade gliomas, we develop a data driven Bayesian framework to define sharp models, and calibrate accurately and efficiently uncertainties associated with the promising biological findings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Bayesian methods we propose in the article (i) are amenable to a flexible class of adaptive models, determined via a complex interplay between signals sifted from variable selection algorithms and domain specific knowledge; (ii) have the advantage of computationally efficient high dimensional inference due to a focus on sharp models with fewer parameters, when compared to their non-adaptive counterparts; (iii) exhibit a significantly better reconciliation between model adaptivity and inferential power than state-of-art approaches, when constrained by the curse of dimensionality. Our main workforce involves a carefully constructed conditional likelihood and utilizes a reparameterization map to obtain compact formulae for a selection-corrected posterior. Deploying our methods to investigate radiogenomic characteristics for diffuse low-grade gliomas, we successfully uncover associations between several biologically important gene pathways and patient survival times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Comparative study of radiologists vs machine learning in differentiating biopsy-proven pseudoprogression and true progression in diffuse gliomas</title>
      <link>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/turk2022comparative/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/turk2022comparative/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Neuroscience Informatics&lt;/em&gt; (2022).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Background and Purpose&lt;/strong&gt; MRI features of tumor progression and
pseudoprogression may be indistinguishable especially without enhancing
portion of the diffuse gliomas. Our aim is to discriminate these two
conditions using radiomics and machine learning algorithm and to compare
them with human observations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Materials and Methods&lt;/strong&gt; Three consecutive MRI studies before a
definitive biopsy in 43 diffuse glioma patients (7 pseudoprogression and
36 true progression cases) who underwent treatment were evaluated. Two
neuroradiologists reviewed pre- and post-contrast T1, T2, FLAIR, ADC,
rCBV, rCBF, K2, and MTT maps. Patterns of enhancement, ADC maps, rCBV,
rCBF, MTT, K2 values, and perilesional FLAIR signal intensity changes
were recorded. Odds ratios (OR) for each descriptor, raters&#39; success in
predicting true and pseudoprogression, and inter-observer reliability
were calculated using the R statistics software. Unpaired Student&amp;rsquo;s
t-test and receiver operating characteristic (ROC) analysis were applied
to compare the texture parameters and histogram analysis of pseudo- and
true progression groups. All first-order and second-order image texture
features and shape features were used to train and test the Random
Forest classifier (RFC). Observers&#39; success and RFC were compared.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Results&lt;/strong&gt; Observers could not identify true progression in the first
visit. However, accuracy of the RFC model was 81%. For the second and
third visits, the rater&amp;rsquo;s success of prediction was between 62% and 72%.
The accuracy for the second and last visit with RFC was 75% and 81%.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusions&lt;/strong&gt; Random Forest classifier was more successful than human
observations in predicting pseudoprogression using MRI.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cellular engagement and interaction in the tumor microenvironment predict non-response to PD-1/PD-L1 inhibitors in metastatic non-small cell lung cancer</title>
      <link>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/qin2022cellular/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/qin2022cellular/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Scientific Reports&lt;/em&gt; (2021).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Immune checkpoint inhibitors (ICI) with anti-PD-1/PD-L1 agents have improved the survival of patients with metastatic non-small cell lung cancer (mNSCLC). Tumor PD-L1 expression is an imperfect biomarker as it does not capture the complex interactions between constituents of the tumor microenvironment (TME). Using multiplex fluorescent immunohistochemistry (mfIHC), we modeled the TME to study the influence of cellular distribution and engagement on response to ICI in mNSCLC. We performed mfIHC on pretreatment tissue from patients with mNSCLC who received ICI. We used primary antibodies against CD3, CD8, CD163, PD-L1, pancytokeratin, and FOXP3; simple and complex phenotyping as well as spatial analyses was performed. We analyzed 68 distinct samples from 52 patients with mNSCLC. Patients were 39&amp;ndash;79 years old (median 67); 44% were male and 75% had adenocarcinoma histology. The most used ICI was atezolizumab (48%). The percentage of PD-L1 positive epithelial tumor cells (EC), degree of cytotoxic T lymphocyte (CTL) engagement with EC, and degree of CTL engagement with helper T lymphocytes (HTL) were significantly lower in non-responders versus responders (p = 0.0163, p = 0.0026 and p = 0.0006, respectively). The combination of these 3 characteristics generated the best sensitivity and specificity to predict non-response to ICI and was also associated with shortened overall survival (p = 0.0271). The combination of low CTL engagement with EC and HTL along with low expression of EC PD-L1 represents a state of impaired endogenous immune reactivity. Together, they more precisely identified non-responders to ICI compared to PD-L1 alone and illustrate the importance of cellular interactions in the TME.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>GaWRDenMap: A quantitative framework to study the local variation in cell-cell interactions in pancreatic disease subtypes</title>
      <link>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/krishnan2022gawrdenmap/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/krishnan2022gawrdenmap/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Scientific Reports&lt;/em&gt; (2022)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Spatial pattern modelling concepts are being increasingly used in capturing disease heterogeneity. Quantification of heterogeneity in the tumor microenvironment is extremely important in pancreatic ductal adenocarcinoma (PDAC), which has been shown to co-occur with other pancreatic diseases and neoplasms with certain attributes that make visual discrimination difficult. In this paper, we propose the GaWRDenMap framework, that utilizes the concepts of geographically weighted regression (GWR) and a density function-based classification model, and apply it to a cohort of multiplex immunofluorescence images from patients belonging to six different pancreatic diseases. We used an internal cohort of 228 patients comprised of 34 Chronic Pancreatitis (CP), 71 PDAC, 70 intraductal papillary mucinous neoplasm (IPMN), 16 mucinous cystic neoplasm (MCN), 29 pancreatic intraductal neoplasia (PanIN) and 8  IPMN-associated PDAC patients. We utilize GWR to model the relationship between epithelial cells and immune cells on a spatial grid. The GWR model estimates were used to generate density signatures which were used in subsequent pairwise classification models to distinguish between any two pairs of disease groups. Image-level, as well as subject-level analysis, were performed. When applied to this dataset, our classification model showed significant discrimination ability in multiple pairwise comparisons, in comparison to commonly used abundance-based metrics, like the Morisita-Horn index. The model was able to  best discriminate between CP and PDAC at both the subject- and image-levels. It was also able to reasonably discriminate between PDAC and IPMN. These results point to a potential difference in the spatial arrangement of epithelial and immune cells between CP, PDAC and IPMN, that could be of high  diagnostic significance. Further validation on a more comprehensive dataset would be warranted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quantifying T2-FLAIR mismatch using geographically weighted regression and predicting molecular status in lower-grade gliomas</title>
      <link>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/mohammed2021quantifying/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/mohammed2021quantifying/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;American Journal of Neuroradiology&lt;/em&gt; (2021).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Nominated for 2021 Lucien Levy Best Research Article.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ajnrblog.org/2022/03/28/journal-announces-this-years-lucien-levy-best-research-article-award-winner-and-nominees/&#34;&gt;AJNR Blog Annoucement&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Background and Purpose&lt;/em&gt;. T2-FLAIR mismatch sign is a validated imaging sign of IDH-mutant 1p/19q non-codeleted gliomas. It is identified by radiologists through visual inspection of pre-operative MRI scans, and has been shown to identify IDH-mutant 1p/19q non-codeleted gliomas with high positive predictive value. We have developed an approach to quantify the T2-FLAIR mismatch signature, and use it to predict molecular status of lower-grade gliomas (LGG).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Materials and Methods&lt;/em&gt;. We used multi-parametric MRI scans and segmentation labels of 108 pre-operative LGG tumors from The Cancer Imaging Archive. Clinical information and T2-FLAIR mismatch sign labels were obtained from supplementary material of relevant publications. We adopted an objective analytical approach to estimate this sign through a geographically weighted regression (GWR), and use the residuals for each case to construct a probability density function (serving as residual signature). These functions are then analyzed using an appropriate statistical framework.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Results&lt;/em&gt;. We observe statistically significant (p-value = 0.05) differences between the averages of residual signatures for IDH-mutated 1p/19q non-codeleted class of tumors versus other categories. Our classifier predicts these cases with area under the curve (AUC) of 0.98, high specificity and sensitivity. It also predicts T2-FLAIR mismatch sign within these cases with an AUC of 0.93.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Conclusions&lt;/em&gt;. Based on this retrospective study, we show that GWR-based residual signatures are highly informative of T2-FLAIR mismatch sign, and can identify IDH mutation and 1p/19q codeletion status with high predictive power. The utility of proposed quantification of T2-FLAIR mismatch sign can be potentially validated through a prospective multi-institutional study.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tumor radiogenomics with Bayesian layered variable selection</title>
      <link>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/mohammed2021tumor/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/mohammed2021tumor/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We propose a statistical framework to integrate radiological magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) and genomic data to identify the underlying radiogenomic associations in lower grade gliomas (LGG). We devise a novel imaging phenotype by dividing the tumor region into concentric spherical layers that mimics the tumor evolution process. MRI data within each layer is represented by voxel&amp;ndash;intensity-based probability density functions which capture the complete information about tumor heterogeneity. Under a Riemannian-geometric framework these densities are mapped to a vector of principal component scores which act as imaging phenotypes. Subsequently, we build Bayesian variable selection models for each layer with the imaging phenotypes as the response and the genomic markers as predictors. Our novel hierarchical prior formulation incorporates the interior-to-exterior structure of the layers, and the correlation between the genomic markers. We employ a computationally-efficient Expectation&amp;ndash;Maximization-based strategy for estimation. Simulation studies demonstrate the superior performance of our approach compared to other approaches. With a focus on the cancer driver genes in LGG, we discuss some biologically relevant findings. Genes implicated with survival and oncogenesis are identified as being associated with the spherical layers, which could potentially serve as early-stage diagnostic markers for disease monitoring, prior to routine invasive approaches.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>RADIOHEAD: Radiogenomic analysis incorporating tumor heterogeneity in imagine through densities</title>
      <link>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/mohammed2021radiohead/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/mohammed2021radiohead/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Annals of Applied Statistics&lt;/em&gt; (2021).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recent technological advancements have enabled detailed investigation of associations between the molecular architecture and tumor heterogeneity, through multi-source integration of radiological imaging and genomic (radiogenomic) data. In this paper, we integrate and harness radiogenomic data in patients with lower grade gliomas (LGG), a type of brain cancer, in order to develop a regression framework called RADIOHEAD (RADIOgenomic analysis incorporating tumor HEterogeneity in imAging through Densities) to identify radiogenomic associations. Imaging data is represented through voxel intensity probability density functions of tumor sub-regions obtained from multimodal magnetic resonance imaging, and genomic data through molecular signatures in the form of pathway enrichment scores corresponding to their gene expression profiles. Employing a Riemannian-geometric framework for principal component analysis on the set of probability densities functions, we map each probability density to a vector of principal component scores, which are then included as predictors in a Bayesian regression model with the pathway enrichment scores as the response. Variable selection compatible with the grouping structure amongst the predictors induced through the tumor sub-regions is carried out under a group spike-and-slab prior. A Bayesian false discovery rate mechanism is then used to infer significant associations based on the posterior distribution of the regression coefficients. Our analyses reveal several pathways relevant to LGG etiology (such as synaptic transmission, nerve impulse and neurotransmitter pathways), to have significant associations with the corresponding imaging-based predictors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Discriminating pseudoprogression and true progression in diffuse infiltrating glioma using multi-parametric MRI data through deep learning</title>
      <link>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/lee2020discriminating/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/lee2020discriminating/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Scientific Reports&lt;/em&gt; (2020).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Differentiating pseudoprogression from true tumor progression has become a significant challenge in follow-up of diffuse infiltrating gliomas, particularly high grade, which leads to a potential treatment delay for patients with early glioma recurrence. In this study, we proposed to use a multiparametric MRI data as a sequence input for the convolutional neural network with the recurrent neural network based deep learning structure to discriminate between pseudoprogression and true tumor progression. In this study, 43 biopsy-proven patient data identified as diffuse infiltrating glioma patients whose disease progressed/recurred were used. The dataset consists of five original MRI sequences; pre-contrast T1-weighted, post-contrast T1-weighted, T2-weighted, FLAIR, and ADC images as well as two engineered sequences; T1post – T1pre and T2 – FLAIR. Next, we used three CNN-LSTM models with a different set of sequences as input sequences to pass through CNN-LSTM layers. We performed 3-fold cross-validation in the training dataset and generated the boxplot, accuracy, and ROC curve, AUC from each trained model with the test dataset to evaluate models. The mean accuracy for VGG16 models ranged from 0.44 to 0.60 and the mean AUC ranged from 0.47 to 0.59. For CNN-LSTM model, the mean accuracy ranged from 0.62 to 0.75 and the mean AUC ranged from 0.64 to 0.81. The performance of the proposed CNN-LSTM with multiparametric sequence data was found to outperform the popular convolutional CNN with a single MRI sequence. In conclusion, incorporating all available MRI sequences into a sequence input for a CNN-LSTM model improved diagnostic performance for discriminating between pseudoprogression and true tumor progression.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Bayesian 2D functional linear model for gray-level co-occurrence matrices in texture analysis of lower grade gliomas</title>
      <link>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/chekouo2020bayesian/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/chekouo2020bayesian/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;NeuroImage: Clinical&lt;/em&gt; (2020).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In cancer radiomics, textural features evaluated from image intensity-derived gray-level co-occurrence matrices (GLCMs) have been studied to evaluate gray-level spatial dependence within the regions of interest in the brain. Most of these analysis work with summary statistics (or texture-based features) constructed using the GLCM entries, and potentially overlook other structural properties in the GLCM.  In our proposed Bayesian framework, we treat each GLCM  as a realization of a two-dimensional stochastic functional process observed with error at discrete time points. The latent process is then combined with the outcome model to evaluate the prediction performance. We use simulation studies to assess the performance of our method and apply it to data collected from individuals with lower grade gliomas. We found our approach to outperform competing methods that use only summary statistics to predict isocitrate dehydrogenase (IDH) mutation status.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Density-based classification in diabetic retinopathy through thickness of retinal layers from optical coherence tomography</title>
      <link>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/mohammed2020density/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/mohammed2020density/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Scientific Reports&lt;/em&gt; (2020).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Diabetic retinopathy (DR) is a severe retinal disorder that can lead to vision loss, however, its underlying mechanism has not been fully understood. Previous studies have taken advantage of Optical Coherence Tomography (OCT) and shown that the thickness of individual retinal layers are affected in patients with DR. However, most studies analyzed the thickness by calculating summary statistics from retinal thickness maps of the macula region. This study aims to apply a density function-based statistical framework to the thickness data obtained through OCT, and to compare the predictive power of various retinal layers to assess the severity of DR. We used a prototype data set of 107 subjects which are comprised of 38 non-proliferative DR (NPDR), 28 without DR (NoDR), and 41 controls. Based on the thickness profiles, we constructed novel features which capture the variation in the distribution of the pixel-wise retinal layer thicknesses from OCT. We quantified the predictive power of each of the retinal layers to distinguish between all three pairwise comparisons of the severity in DR (NoDR vs NPDR, controls vs NPDR and controls vs NoDR). When applied to this preliminary DR data set, our density-based method demonstrated better predictive results compared with simple summary statistics. Furthermore, our results indicate considerable differences in retinal layer structuring based on the severity of DR. We found that: (a) the outer plexiform layer is the most discriminative layer for classifying NoDR vs NPDR; (b) the outer plexiform, inner nuclear and ganglion cell layers are the strongest biomarkers for discriminating controls from NPDR; and (c) the inner nuclear layer distinguishes best between controls and NoDR.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
