<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Journal Articles | Shariq Mohammed</title>
    <link>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/tags/journal-articles/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/tags/journal-articles/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Journal Articles</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 30 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>Journal Articles</title>
      <link>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/tags/journal-articles/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Discriminating pseudoprogression and true progression in diffuse infiltrating glioma using multi-parametric MRI data through deep learning</title>
      <link>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/lee2020discriminating/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/lee2020discriminating/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Scientific Reports&lt;/em&gt; (Just Accepted).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Differentiating pseudoprogression from true tumor progression has become a significant challenge in follow-up of diffuse infiltrating gliomas, particularly high grade, which leads to a potential treatment delay for patients with early glioma recurrence. In this study, we proposed to use a multiparametric MRI data as a sequence input for the convolutional neural network with the recurrent neural network based deep learning structure to discriminate between pseudoprogression and true tumor progression. In this study, 43 biopsy-proven patient data identified as diffuse infiltrating glioma patients whose disease progressed/recurred were used. The dataset consists of five original MRI sequences; pre-contrast T1-weighted, post-contrast T1-weighted, T2-weighted, FLAIR, and ADC images as well as two engineered sequences; T1post – T1pre and T2 – FLAIR. Next, we used three CNN-LSTM models with a different set of sequences as input sequences to pass through CNN-LSTM layers. We performed 3-fold cross-validation in the training dataset and generated the boxplot, accuracy, and ROC curve, AUC from each trained model with the test dataset to evaluate models. The mean accuracy for VGG16 models ranged from 0.44 to 0.60 and the mean AUC ranged from 0.47 to 0.59. For CNN-LSTM model, the mean accuracy ranged from 0.62 to 0.75 and the mean AUC ranged from 0.64 to 0.81. The performance of the proposed CNN-LSTM with multiparametric sequence data was found to outperform the popular convolutional CNN with a single MRI sequence. In conclusion, incorporating all available MRI sequences into a sequence input for a CNN-LSTM model improved diagnostic performance for discriminating between pseudoprogression and true tumor progression.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Predictions, role of interventions and effects of a historic national lockdown in India’s response to the COVID-19 pandemic: data science call to arms</title>
      <link>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/ray2020predictions/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/ray2020predictions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Harvard Data Science Review&lt;/em&gt; (2020).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With only 536 cases and 11 fatalities, India took the historic decision of a 21-day national lockdown on March 25. The lockdown was first extended to May 3 soon after the analysis of this paper was completed, and then to May 18 while this paper was being revised. In this paper, we use a Bayesian extension of the Susceptible-Infected-Removed (eSIR) model designed for intervention forecasting to study the short- and long-term impact of an initial 21-day lockdown on the total number of COVID-19 infections in India compared to other less severe non-pharmaceutical interventions. We compare effects of hypothetical durations of lockdown on reducing the number of active and new infections. We find that the lockdown, if implemented correctly, can reduce the total number of cases in the short term, and buy India invaluable time to prepare its healthcare and disease-monitoring system. Our analysis shows we need to have some measures of suppression in place after the lockdown for increased benefit (as measured by reduction in the number of cases). A longer lockdown between 42-56 days is preferable to substantially “flatten the curve” when compared to 21-28 days of lockdown. Our models focus solely on projecting the number of COVID-19 infections and thus, inform policymakers about one aspect of this multi-faceted decision-making problem. We conclude with a discussion on the pivotal role of increased testing, reliable and transparent data, proper uncertainty quantification, accurate interpretation of forecasting models, reproducible data science methods and tools that can enable data-driven policymaking during a pandemic. Our software products are available at &lt;a href=&#34;covind19.org&#34;&gt;covind19.org&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
