<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Thierry Chekouo | Shariq Mohammed</title>
    <link>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/authors/thierry-chekouo/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/authors/thierry-chekouo/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Thierry Chekouo</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 01 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>Thierry Chekouo</title>
      <link>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/authors/thierry-chekouo/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bayesian group selection with compositional responses for analysis of radiologic tumor proportions and their genomic determinants</title>
      <link>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/chekouo2023bayesian/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/chekouo2023bayesian/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Annals of Applied Statistics&lt;/em&gt; (2023).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Volumetric imaging features are used in cancer research to determine the size and the composition of a tumor and have been shown to be prognostic of overall survival. In this paper we focus on the analysis of tumor component proportions of brain cancer patients collected through The Cancer Genome Atlas (TCGA) project. Our main goal is to identify pathways and corresponding genes that can explain the heterogeneity of the composition of a brain tumor. In particular, we focus on the glioblastoma multiform (GBM), as it is the most common malignant brain neoplasm, accounting for 23% of all primary brain tumors for which it still has very poor prognosis. We propose a Bayesian hierarchical model for variable selection with a group structure in the context of correlated multivariate compositional response variables. More specifically, we model the proportions of the tumor components within the tumor using a Dirichlet model by allowing for straightforward incorporation of available high-dimensional covariate information within a log-linear regression framework. We impose prior distributions that account for the overlapping structure between groups of covariates. Simulations and application to GBM disease show the importance of our approach. We have identified associations between tumor component volume-based features and several important pathways and genes. Some of these genes have previously been shown to be prognostic indicators of overall survival time in GBM.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Bayesian 2D functional linear model for gray-level co-occurrence matrices in texture analysis of lower grade gliomas</title>
      <link>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/chekouo2020bayesian/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shariq-mohammed.github.io/publication/chekouo2020bayesian/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;NeuroImage: Clinical&lt;/em&gt; (2020).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In cancer radiomics, textural features evaluated from image intensity-derived gray-level co-occurrence matrices (GLCMs) have been studied to evaluate gray-level spatial dependence within the regions of interest in the brain. Most of these analysis work with summary statistics (or texture-based features) constructed using the GLCM entries, and potentially overlook other structural properties in the GLCM.  In our proposed Bayesian framework, we treat each GLCM  as a realization of a two-dimensional stochastic functional process observed with error at discrete time points. The latent process is then combined with the outcome model to evaluate the prediction performance. We use simulation studies to assess the performance of our method and apply it to data collected from individuals with lower grade gliomas. We found our approach to outperform competing methods that use only summary statistics to predict isocitrate dehydrogenase (IDH) mutation status.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
